INSTRUCTOR: In this lecture, we present
Holistic Artificial Intelligence for Medicine, or HAIM for short.
Haim is the Jewish word for life.
It represents an application of multimodal AI in medicine.
The outline of the lecture is as follows.
We first give motivation for using multimodal AI.
We then present HAIM and apply it
in a real-world environment at Hartford HealthCare system.
And finally, we conclude with applications of HAIM
in several other areas of medicine.
To motivate multimodality,
let us think about how medical doctors make decisions.
They utilize scans, MRIs, CTs, X-rays, et cetera; language,
radiology reports, doctors' or nurses' notes;
tabular data, electronic medical records, for instance;
time series; and genomic information.
Given that human doctors use multimodal data,
it is natural to ask whether machines
can use multimodal data to make medical diagnoses and decisions.
Consider the sensors that humans use to understand the world.
People use the five basic human senses--
touch, sight, hearing, smell, and taste.
In other words, multimodality is a fundamental characteristic
of human life.
It is therefore natural to consider the question
whether machines should also use multimodal data.
In this lecture, we present HAIM based on the principal findings
of a 2022 paper titled "Integrated Multimodal
Artificial Intelligence Framework for Healthcare
Applications" that appeared in Nature Digital Medicine,
in September 2022, by myself and members of my research group.
I would like to tell you a bit of the history
of the conception of HAIM.
In 2013, IBM created Watson, a computer program that
could compete in Jeopardy, a game
in which a contestant is given a statement
and she needs to express the answer
in the form of a question.
For example, if the answer is "he developed the theory
of relativity," the contestant needs to say, for a correct
answer, "who is Albert Einstein?"
IBM Watson competed with the best human players in history
over two days, and it won very decisively.
I remember the excitement of this event,
as I knew at the time that this was
the beginning of an era propelling machine
intelligence to the next level.
IBM proceeded to apply Watson in medicine,
unfortunately unsuccessfully.
In the intervening 12 years, artificial intelligence
has advanced significantly, especially generative AI
and large language models.
HAIM shows how to combine various modalities
to achieve significantly improved performance.
HAIM presents a holistic perspective of AI--
computer vision, natural language processing,
machine learning-- to improve the ability of models
to make predictions and prescriptions,
especially in medicine.
The traditional machine learning paradigm
is to use tabular data for making predictions.
When multiple modalities are present,
like computer vision or language,
this paradigm does not apply and we
need to discover different ways of combining data.
In the next slides, we outline how
to combine different modalities of data.
When electronic health data are present,
like the one shown in the slide, we keep the records as they are,
as they are in the traditional machine learning format,
where traditional methods apply.
When there are time series available,
we use software like tsfresh--
you will see now in the recitation--
to extract features of the time series,
like the maximum value, the minimum value, the median,
the mean, the number of peaks, among many others.
In this way, the time series is summarized into numbers
that serve as inputs in a traditional machine learning format.
When the inputs are doctor or nurse
notes or a radiology report, that is, language,
we use a foundation model like ClinicalBERT.
This summarizes the language information in the format
of an embedding, a 768-element vector.
This vector summarizes the information
in numerical format that can be combined
with other numerical features.
Note that we can use generative AI
models like OpenAI 4.0 or Llama instead of ClinicalBERT.
When the input is an electronic cardiogram,
we use the language information included in the EKG,
like language, and then use a foundation model like
ClinicalBERT, as we have seen earlier,
that summarizes the language information in the format
of an embedding of a 768-element vector in numerical format,
as before.
When the input is an image like an X-ray,
we use convolutional neural networks to extract an embedding
of a 768-element vector in numerical format.
Note that we can use embeddings from a generative AI model,
instead of using images from a CNN model as an alternative.
This is the critical idea of the lecture.
We use the numerical features we developed, either directly
from electronic health care records
or extracted features from time series or embeddings
using unstructured data.
This idea is called fusion.
We now have a traditional machine learning task.
We want to predict, say, for example, mortality using
as inputs the numerical features we extracted,
as indicated earlier.
We use a traditional ML model like XGBoost or random forest
to perform this prediction task.
Note that the method is very general,
as we treat each modality independently,
so that if we add new modalities,
we just add the additional embeddings.
Note that we do not train the modalities in combination.
Note also that the embeddings do not depend
on the task we want to perform.
The embeddings just summarize the data
of each modality independently of the task we want to perform.
Let us now apply HAIM for various prediction tasks using
MIMIC-IV data set from the Beth Israel Deaconess Medical
Center, a hospital system in Boston, Massachusetts.
The data set of 34,537 patient records comes from
the emergency ICU rooms.
The records include a chest X-ray,
electronic medical records, radiology notes, and EKG.
That is, it includes vision, language, and tabular data.
Our target diagnoses include 12 targets--
mortality prediction, that is, we
aim to predict if a patient is deceased or sent to hospice
or the patient is alive at the hospital discharge; one
of 10 diagnoses, that is, we want to predict if a patient has
a certain disease, like fracture, lung lesion, enlarge
CM, consolidation, pneumonia, [INAUDIBLE] classes, lung
capacity, pneumothorax, edema, cardiomegaly; and finally,
the length of stay, that is, we want
to predict if a patient exits the hospital in 48 hours.
We have compared the performance of HAIM
and the performance of a classical machine learning model
that is only based on electronic medical records,
the classical approach.
On mortality, HAIM improves the accuracy by 11% to 33%
compared to electronic medical records.
That is only based on classical machine learning models.
On disease classification, HAIM improves the accuracy
by 6% to 22% compared to electronic records.
On length of stay, HAIM improves the accuracy by 8% to 20%
compared to electronic medical records
and a more classical machine learning model.
In all cases, the use of multimodality
results in a significant improvement of performance.
In this slide, we present subanalyses in order
to understand the relative contribution of each modality
to the prediction for disease classification.
The vision input, in this case, the X-ray,
was the dominant modality.
For length of stay and mortality,
the time series and the electronic medical records
were the dominant modalities.
We next present an application of the HAIM methodology
to predict length of stay at Hartford Health Care system,
HHC for short, the largest hospital system in Connecticut,
with operating revenues above $5 billion a year,
seven diverse hospitals, ranging from an academic urban hospital
to a community hospital, and from large to small hospitals.
Altogether, HHC has a total of 2,500 beds.
It is representative of a high-quality, typical US
hospital network.
We have implemented some of the algorithms we presented
in a company called Holistic Hospital Optimization,
H2O for short.
This is an indication of the connections
with the fundamental aspect of life, water.
We discuss in detail the length-of-stay application.
We have implemented other applications,
like a deterioration index, that includes mortality risk, ICU
risk, scheduling nurses, and scheduling operating rooms.
The software is used by hundreds of users--
physicians, nurses, administrators.
It works in all seven hospitals of HHC,
and has led to an annual revenue uplift in the tens of millions
of dollars.
We have implemented these solutions
in several other hospital systems around the world.
The applications include predicting
discharge in the next 24 or 48 hours, which
is important for identifying and prioritizing patients,
reducing the length of stay, saving costs,
and preparing for treatment and disposition plans.
It also predicts the final destination
after discharge, the mortality risk,
as well as the risk of needing admission to the intensive care
unit.
These predictions help warn of patient deterioration,
as well as allocate hospital resources more effectively.
The table depicts the AUC, the Area Under the Curve,
for mortality, destination, 24- and 48-hour discharge,
predicting entering ICU or leaving ICU for all seven
hospitals at HHC.
The results are reliably strong across all predictions
and all hospitals.
We next demonstrate that the calibration plots are also
very accurate.
Specifically, in the left plot, on the horizontal axis,
we plot the proportion of patients that have a probability
of 48-hour discharge between, say, 0.5 and 0.6,
in increments of 10%, and on the
vertical
axis we plot the proportion of those patients who are discharged within 48 hours.
The line is very close to the 45-degree angle,
illustrating that the predicted probabilities closely match
empirical evidence.
On the right plot, we show the calibration plot for mortality.
Again, calibration is very accurate.
The figure shows the software that
has been implemented at HHC.
The colors demonstrate the following information.
Green suggests that the patient needs
to be prioritized for discharge.
Yellow also indicates that hospital personnel
need to prepare, but not with the same level of intensity.
Red indicates that the patient is deteriorating.
Note that we assign a green alert
if the discharge probability in the next 24 hours or 48 hours
is over 50%.
The yellow alert happens if the 48-hour discharge probability is
between 35% and 50%, and the probability increases by over
10% from the day before.
The software also plots a subplot
that shows how different factors affect length of stay.
This way, the predictions are far more interpretable.
Compared with human doctors, the artificial intelligence approach
has significantly higher AUC, identifies
more patients who can be discharged,
and makes more accurate predictions.
Clearly, the AI edge is significant.
We have performed a test in which certain wards at HHC
have used the software and compared it with others
that did not use it.
We have found that the average patient
length of stay for the units that use the software
was reduced by 0.67 days, from 565 to 498 days.
This suggests that we reduce length
of stay approximately 15%, and thus we
can increase the throughput by a corresponding amount,
thus increasing the overall revenue of the hospital
by tens of millions annually.
HAIM is widely applicable in a variety of applications.
Examples of current work include detecting domestic abuse
at the Brigham and Women's Hospital, automatic detection
of data from nodes, scans, and laboratories
at Mass General Brigham, unified diagnostics for EKG at Hartford
Hospital, detection of subdural hematoma,
as well as what is called AI companion.
We utilize HAIM to give advice to doctors and nurses regarding
diagnosis.