INSTRUCTOR: So far, we have analyzed the single variable,
students' heights.
This type of analysis is called univariate analysis, which
has a goal to describe and summarize the variables
characteristics using descriptive statistics,
things like mean, median, standard deviation,
and visualizations, plots such as histograms and box plots.
In bivariate analysis, we explore two variables
and their relationship.
And in multivariate analysis, we look at three or more variables
simultaneously and again, try to understand
their, this time, more complex, potentially, relationships.
So let's move from our univariate analysis
of students' heights to bivariate analysis, which
in addition to the heights data, also includes students' weights.
Now, we have two observational variables.
And it is interesting to quantify
the relationship between them--
that is, to measure how the variables covary.
Weights, and heights are related to each other.
Taller students tend to weigh more than shorter students.
We can plot that, one variable on the x-axis
and the other on the y-axis.
This kind of plot is called a scatter plot.
Each dot represents one student.
The great thing about scatter plots
is that they help us see patterns,
how the two variables relate to each other.
In the figure, we can observe an increasing pattern
from left to right.
This means that weights and heights are positively
correlated with each other.
This type of relationship is also
called an association in bivariate analysis.
A linear association means the points form more or less
a straight line.
However, we can also observe non-linear associations,
such as quadratic patterns.
And sometimes there is no clear patterns,
as we can see in the figure.
In addition to the form of the association,
we also care about the direction.
If the slope of the line is upward,
it means the association is positive.
If the slope is downward, the association is negative.
We also care about the strength of the association.
If the points are tightly clustered around the line,
it is a strong association.
If the points are more spread out, the association is weak.
It is important to note that strength does not
depend on direction.
You can have a strong positive or
a strong negative association.
We can also quantify both the strength and direction
of a linear association using the correlation coefficient,
which ranges from minus 1 to 1.
The closer the value is to 1 or minus 1,
the stronger the linear relationship.
A value near 0 means there is little or no linear association.
For instance, a strong positive correlation might be around 0.9.
If the variables are unrelated, we
might see something like 0.01.
However, we should keep in mind that correlation does not
imply causation.
Just because two things move together
does not mean that one causes the other.
Even in our example, where height and weight are related,
the relationship is not directly causal.
Yes, they are correlated, but height does not directly
cause weight.
Instead, shared underlying factors like age, nutrition,
and biology influence both.
We can also use covariance to measure how
two variables vary together.
The covariance is positive if they
increase or decrease together.
It is negative if one increases while the other decreases.
And the covariance is near 0 if there is no consistent pattern.
Both covariance and correlation are summary statistics
that describe how two sets of observations
relate to each other.
Covariance gives us the direction of the relationship,
but not the strength in a meaningful way,
while correlation helps us quantify
both direction and strength of a linear relationship.
Now, let's talk about a classic statistical phenomenon,
Simpson's paradox.
Suppose we collect data on student height
and how many points they score in basketball.
When we look at the overall data,
it might appear that these two variables are negatively
correlated.
That is, taller students seem to score fewer points.
Hm.
However, when we separate the data
into two subgroups, male and female,
we may find that within each group,
taller students tend to score more points.
So the overall data suggests a negative correlation,
but the subgroup data reveals positive correlations
in both groups.
What does that mean?
It means that there is another factor, another variable--
in this case, gender--
that influences the observed relationship.
This variable is called the confounding variable.
In terms of terminology, we refer
to height as the independent variable and basketball points
as the dependent variable.
So the essence of the Simpson's paradox
is that if we ignore subgroups, like gender, in this case,
the overall trend might be misleading.
In other words, a trend that appears
in different groups of data disappears or reverses
when the groups are combined.
It's a statistical illusion caused
by these lurking or confounding variables that affect
the observed relationship.
This paradox is another important reminder
that correlation does not imply causation.
Now, contrast that with a classic example
of a spurious correlation.
Ice cream sales and shark attacks.
These two variables are correlated.
But does eating ice cream cause shark attacks?
Of course not.
The real explanation is a third factor.
Hot weather increases both ice cream sales and beach
activity, which, in turn, raises the chances of shark attacks.
This is what we call a spurious or misleading correlation, when
two variables appear related, but the connection is actually
driven by an external factor.
To sum up from today's lecture, we
talked about how to visualize data
with histograms, box plots, and scatter plots,
and explored key ideas like central tendency, spread,
and relationships between variables.
So far, we've looked at how variables can be associated--
not just the direction, but also the form and strength
of those relationships.
Then we moved into correlation and covariance
as tools to quantify those patterns.
In the end, statistics isn't just about calculating numbers.
It is about making decisions under uncertainty
and doing it in a way that's careful, clear, and transparent.
See you in the next lecture.